Finding Aid for James J. Duderstadt Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- Paper Documents
  - Topical Files, 1969-1991; 1.5 linear feet
    The Topical Files is limited in scope, holding papers mainly from Dr. Duderstadt's involvement on various committees within the Department of Nuclear Engineering. The bulk of these materials are from the years just preceding his appointment to Dean of the College of Engineering. An interesting, yet not dated, written document titled, "Thoughts on A Rainy Day, on moving the College of Engineering to North Campus" may be the initial seed for the ultimate move of the College of Engineering from central campus to the North Campus in the mid-1980s. The remainder of the series is comprised of papers associated with his term as provost. The largest file is entitled "Contacts," and includes memos, cards and letters, message slips, lists of meeting attendees, hand-written notes, and other miscellany. Of particular significance is a list of key activities for 1981 to 1985 relating to Duderstadt's accomplishments in the College of Engineering, and the farewell address (with annotations) that he gave to engineering staff upon leaving. Also important are notes entitled "Vision of the University" that Duderstadt prepared while he was being considered for the provost position. In addition, there is a small correspondence file, significant partly because there is so little "traditional" correspondence from his year's as president in the collection as a whole. The 2003 accession added one linear feet of material concerning Duderstadt's role on the National Science Board in the early 1990s.
    - Contacts (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1983-1988 (Box 16)
    - Farewell Address (College of Engineering), April 7, 1986 (Box 16)
    - Notes, 1981-1986 (Box 16)
    - American Nuclear Society
      - Planning Committee, Publication Reports (Box 16)
      - Agendas and Meeting Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 16)
      - Michigan Section Correspondence, 1979 (Box 16)
      - Membership Direction, Michigan Section (Box 16)
    - Academic Affairs Advisory Committee
      - Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 16)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1977-1979 (Box 16)
    - College of Engineering History file, undated (Box 16)
    - Committee on Public Administration, 1979 (Box 16)
    - Course and Academic Program material, 1976-1979 (Box 16)
    - Curriculum Committee reports, 1973-1979 (Box 16)
    - Departmental Review Committee, correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 16)
    - Department of Nuclear Engineering, Departmental Materials, miscellaneous, 1971-1975 (Box 16)
    - Department of Nuclear Engineering Review Background Material, circa 1979 (Box 16)
    - Department of Nuclear Engineering Review Committee Report, February 1979 (Box 16)
    - Employment Patterns for Nuclear Engineering, 1975-1977 (Box 16)
    - Engineering-Mathematics Committee, 1969-1983 (Box 16)
    - Engineering-Mathematics-Statistics Committee, Agendas and Meeting Minutes, 1975-1983 (Box 16)
    - Evaluations of Faculty Research Grants, 1975-1979 (Box 16)
    - Evaluation of Faculty Research Grants Report, 1979 (Box 16)
    - Faculty Awards, 1977-1979 (Box 16)
    - Faculty Search Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 16)
    - A Guide to Nuclear Engineering Students Interested in Fission Reactors, undated (Box 16)
    - Prelim Committee, 1976-1979 (Box 17)
    - A Proposal for Master's Level Education In Remote Sensing, Rackham Executive Committee, 1979 (Box 17)
    - Rackham Executive Board, 1978-1979 (Box 17)
    - Report of the Ad Hoc Space Committee, Cooley Laboratory Move, circa 1977 (Box 17)
    - Report of the Ad Hoc Committee to Review the Department of Mechanical Engineering, 1978 (Box 17)
    - Report on Inter-College Programs, undated (Box 17)
    - A Report on Research Incentives, Advisory Committee on Academic Affairs, 1979-1980 (Box 17)
    - Report of the Subcommittee to review the University Extension Service, 1981 (Box 17)
    - Subcommittee to review the University Extension Service, background materials and correspondence, 1981; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Rules of the Faculty of the College of Engineering, 1973 (Box 17)
    - Thoughts on a Rainy Day, on moving the College of Engineering to North Campus, undated (Box 17)
    - National Academy of Engineering, November 1987 (Box 24)
    - National Science Board
      - Appointment materials, ca., 1985 (Box 24)
      - Meeting Minutes and Related Materials
        - 1990, 2 folders (Box 24)
        - 1991 (Box 24)
        - 1992 (Box 24)
        - 1993 (Box 24)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposal, Management and Operation of the NSFNET Backbone Network, August 1987 (Box 24)
    - Presentations, 1991 (Box 24)
  - Teaching, 1966-1981; 2.5 linear feet
    The Teaching series works hand-in-hand with the Research series. Where the Research series shows Duderstadt's intense interest in scientific discovery, the Teaching series shows how he conveyed this knowledge to a broad audience. The series contains nuclear engineering lecture material and assignments as well as material on seminars taught by Duderstadt such as the UM-Bendix Engineering Summer conference and the Consumer's Power Nuclear Engineering Program that was held in 1980. The series also contains background materials and scripts for the University of Michigan Television Center program "Nuclear Power and You" that was taped in the late 1970s and which featured Duderstadt.
    - Argonne National Laboratory, 1975-1979 (Box 17)
    - Class Assignments, various dates (Box 17)
    - Commonwealth Associates Reactor Course, 1973 (Box 17)
    - Computers in Engineering Education, 1980 (Box 17)
    - Course descriptions, various dates (Box 17)
    - Course lecture material, undated (Box 17)
    - Course material for Nuclear Engineering 441, undated (Box 17)
    - Course material for Nuclear Engineering 511, 1970 (Box 17)
    - Course material for Nuclear Engineering 695, undated (Box 17)
    - Energy Forum, 1980 (Box 17)
    - General Energy Education workshop, 1978 (Box 17)
    - High School Seminars, 1973 (Box 17)
    - Lecture Material
      - Material, Undated (Box 17)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 17)
      - 1975 (Box 17)
      - Development of Nuclear Power, 1979 (Box 18)
      - E.C.E. 426: Reactions in Plasma Physics* *or, How not to spend fall weekends in Ann Arbor, 1973-1974 (Box 18)
      - Fundamentals of Transport Theory, Ecole D'ete' D'Analyse Numerique, June-July, 1981 (Box 18)
      - Inertial Confinement Fusion, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Kinetic Theory, 1976 (Box 18)
      - Laser Fusion, 1971; 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Laser-Plasma, 1971 (Box 18)
      - Nuclear Engineering 643, 1976; 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Nuclear Engineering 644: Transport Theory, 1977 (Box 18)
      - Nuclear Engineering Colloquium, Fall 1973 (Box 18)
      - Overheads and Equations, circa 1968 (Box 18)
      - Waves, Pulses, and Noise, 1966-1969 (Box 18)
    - Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory, circa 1971 (Box 18)
    - Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory, undated (Box 18)
    - National Aeronautics and Space Administration Intensive Course on Lasers, 1972 (Box 18)
    - Nuclear Education Program, Consumer's Power project, 1980-1981 (Box 19)
    - Nuclear Engineering Curriculum, scattered dates (Box 19)
    - Nuclear Engineering examinations, various dates (Box 19)
    - N.E. 562 Student Papers, 1980 (Box 19)
    - N.E. 599 Student Paper, 1971 (Box 19)
    - N.E. Ph.D. Candidates
      - Adalioglu, Ulvi, circa 1971 (Box 19)
      - Sidney Karin, circa 1971 (Box 19)
      - Russ Mosteller, circa 1971 (Box 19)
      - William Price, circa 1970 (Box 19)
      - Paul Turinsky, circa 1971 (Box 19)
    - Sanoia Comments, circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - Seminars
      - Inertial Confinement Fusion Schemes, circa 1977 (Box 19)
      - Laser-Fusion, 1977 (Box 19)
      - Nuclear Power: Realities and Myths, circa 1976 (Box 19)
      - The Role of the Finite Element Method in Radiation Physics, circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - Student Course Evaluations, circa 1977 (Box 19)
    - Student Study Guide for Principles of Engineering, undated (Box 19)
    - Summer School on the Transport Equation, Ecole D'ete D'Analyse Numerique, circa 1980 (Box 19)
    - UM-Bendix Engineering Summer Conference, 1979 (Box 19)
    - University of Michigan Television Center (UMTV), background material for "Nuclear Power and You" program, circa 1978 (Box 19)
    - UMTV: "Nuclear Power and You," scripts (Box 19)
    - United States Department of Energy Workshop on General Energy Education, circa 1978 (Box 19)
    - Utility Nuclear Engineering Summer Course, undated (Box 19)
    - Photographs, 4 envelopes
      - Illustrations used in Publications (Box 19)
      - Neutron Transport Theory Conference, Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory, 1971 (Box 19)
      - Photographs used in Publications. Computers; data centers; Detroit Edison Plant, Monroe, Michigan; disk storage unit; Enrico Fermi 2, Monroe, Michigan; graphics display unit; magnetic tape unit (Box 19)
      - University of Michigan Computer Laboratory with students, unidentified and undated (Box 19)
      - Slides used in Publications, 5 slides (Box 19)
  - Presidential Transition Files, 1988; 2 linear feet
    The Presidential Transition Files series consists largely of the working files of the inauguration committee for the 11th President of the University of Michigan. These files include material on the invitation list, program, seating arrangements and other logistical issues. In addition to working files, the series contains some correspondence to Duderstadt on the announcement of his appointment as 11th President of the University of Michigan, the inauguration address, and thanks you's sent from the Duderstadt's after the inauguration. Newsclippings relating to the inauguration are especially complete and arranged chronologically by month. Also of particular note are printed materials designed especially for the inauguration and related events. Printed material includes the invitation and program
    - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 20)
      - Congratulations and Presidential Thank-You's, June-September 1988; 10 folders (Box 20)
    - Electronic mail congratulations, paper printouts, 1988 (Box 20)
    - Inauguration, (June-October 1988) (Box 21)
      - Acceptances (Box 21)
      - Address (Box 21)
      - Committee, Working Papers, September 27, 1988 (Box 21)
      - Correspondence (Box 21)
      - Delegates (Box 21)
      - Hill Auditorium (Box 21)
      - Ingalls Reception (Box 21)
      - Invitation Lists (Box 21)
      - Recommendations for, 2 folders
      - Invitation Sub-Committee (Box 21)
      - Logistics (Box 21)
      - Marshalls (Box 21)
      - Power Center Reception (Box 21)
      - Preparation, Task List and Assignments (Box 21)
      - Printed Materials (e.g. Invitation, Schedule of Events, Program) (Box 21)
      - Program (Box 21)
      - Regent's Luncheon (Box 21)
      - Remarks by C.M. Vest (Box 21)
      - Seating Plans (Box 21)
      - Student Events (Box 21)
      - Thank you's (post inauguration) (Box 21)
    - News Coverage, June-October 1988; 5 folders (Box 21)
  - Strategic Planning, 1986-1996; 0.75 linear feet
    The series Strategic Planning includes materials mainly from the first few years of Duderstadt's presidential tenure. This series includes background materials on the Michigan Mandate and Michigan Plan as well as reference notebooks used in strategic planning meetings. Related strategic planning material can be found in the Strategy subseries within the Univeristy of Michigan Presidency series.
    - Diversity Readings, general, scattered dates. (Box 23)
    - Faculty Diversity, University of California Study, September 1987 (Box 23)
    - Michigan Commitment, background materials, ca., 1988 (Box 23)
    - Michigan Mandate and related materials, ca., 1988; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Michigan Plan, presentation and associated materials, ca., 1988 (Box 23)
    - Strategy Files, general, ca., 1988 (Box 23)
    - Strategic Planning
      - Reference Notebooks, ca., 1986-1996; 3 folders, 2 volumes (Box 23)
      - Summary Notes on Schools and Colleges, ca., 1985-1986 (Box 23)
    - Strategic Planning Team, Agendas and Meeting Minutes, circa 1987-1988 (Box 23)
  - Diaries and Notebooks, 1981-1996; 5 linear feet
    The Diaries and Notebooks series consists of 43 diaries that James Duderstadt kept during his time as dean of the College of Engineering, Provost and Vice President for Academic Affairs, and President of the University of Michigan. The volumes are arranged chronologically by the semester each diary covered, while some semesters during his presidency spanned two volumes.
    Each diary documents meetings and projects in which Duderstadt was involved. Volumes from Duderstadt's tenure as the dean of the College of Engineering and Provost primarily contains handwritten notes from committee meetings, discussing projects and the university's organizational structure. The volumes covering Duderstadt's time as president include meeting agendas, emails, and newspaper clippings regarding the University of Michigan.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted until July 1, 2037
    - Dean of the College of Engineering
      - Winter Semester, 1981; 1 volume (Box 25)
        Restricted until July 01, 2037
      - Spring Semester, 1981; 1 volume (Box 25)
      - Summer Semester, 1981; 1 volume (Box 25)
      - Fall Semester, 1981; 1 volume (Box 25)
      - Winter Semester, 1982; 1 volume (Box 25)
      - Spring Semester, 1982; 1 volume (Box 25)
      - Fall Semester, 1982; 1 volume (Box 25)
      - Winter Semester, 1983; 1 volume (Box 25)
      - Spring Semester, 1983; 1 volume (Box 25)
      - Fall Semester, 1983; 1 volume (Box 25)
      - Winter Semester, 1984 (Box 25)
      - Spring Semester, 1984; 1 volume (Box 25)
      - Fall Semester, 1984; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Winter Semester, 1985; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Spring Semester, 1985; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Fall Semester, 1985; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Winter Semester, 1986; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Spring Semester, 1986
        - Volume 1 of 2, April 1986; 1 volume (Box 26)
        - Volume 2 of 2, 1986; 1 volume (Box 26)
    - Provost and Vice President for Academic Affairs
      - Summer Semester, 1986; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Fall Semester, 1986; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Winter Semester, 1987; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Spring Semester, 1987; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Fall Semester, 1987; 1 volume (Box 26)
      - Winter and Spring Semesters, 1988; 1 volume (Box 27)
    - President
      - Fall Semester, 1988; 1 volume (Box 27)
      - Winter and Spring Semesters, 1989; 1 volume (Box 27)
      - Fall Semester, 1990; 1 volume (Box 27)
      - Winter Semester, 1990; 1 volume (Box 27)
      - Spring Semester, 1990; 1 volume (Box 27)
      - Winter Semester, 1991; 1 volume (Box 27)
      - Spring Semester, 1991; 1 volume (Box 27)
      - Fall Semester, 1991; 1 volume (Box 27)
      - Winter Semester, 1992; 1 volume (Box 27)
      - Fall Semester, 1992; 1 volume (Box 28)
      - Spring Semester, 1992; 1 volume (Box 28)
      - Winter Semester, 1993; 1 volume (Box 28)
      - Spring Semester, 1993; 1 volume (Box 28)
      - Summer Semester, 1993; 1 volume (Box 28)
      - Fall Semester, 1993; 1 volume (Box 28)
      - Winter Semester, 1994; 1 volume (Box 28)
      - Spring Semester, 1994; 1 volume (Box 28)
      - Summer Semester, 1994; 1 volume (Box 28)
      - Fall Semester, 1994
        - Volume 1 of 2, 1 volume (Box 28)
        - Volume 2 of 2, 1 volume (Box 29)
      - Winter Semester, 1995; 1 volume (Box 29)
      - Spring Semester, 1995; 1 volume (Box 29)
      - Summer Semester, 1995; 1 volume (Box 29)
      - Fall Semester, 1995
        - Volume 1 of 2, 1 volume (Box 29)
        - Volume 2 of 2, 1 volume (Box 29)
      - Winter Semester, 1996
        - Volume 1 of 2, 1 volume (Box 29)
        - Volume 2 of 2, 1 volume (Box 29)
      - Spring Semester, 1996; 1 volume (Box 29)
- Digital Documents
  The Digital Documents subgroup is made up of a University of Michigan Presidency series and a Faculty Archives series.
  - University of Michigan Presidency, 1986-1997; 5397 original digital files (393 MB)
    There are 5397 original digital files (393 MB) in the University of Michigan Presidency series. At the time of the records accession to the Bentley Historical Library, the Macintosh operating system version 8.0 was in use. The original organization and arrangement of Duderstadt's digital files has been preserved. Duderstadt maintained seven archival directories: Speeches, Idea Files, Strategy, Position Papers, Presentations, Write Files, and Legacy. An additional series, Digital Images, was created when a collection of digital images of university building projects was accessioned to the collection early in 1998.
    The arrangement of files within each directory is chronological by date starting with the 1986-1987 school year. This arrangement was designed and used by Duderstadt in the Speeches, Idea Files, and Write Files series and extended to the remaining series except the Digital Images during the processing phase of the project. The directory naming scheme effectively describes the type of record contained within the directory. File names are also in most cases descriptive of the content, however, researchers should note that Duderstadt used personal last names, initials, abbreviations, and numerous acronyms in naming files. A list of commonly used acronyms and abbreviations used for file naming purposes can be found in the 'Additional Descriptive Data' section of the finding aid. Researcher's Note: The file-naming scheme also reveals the specific version of a particular document. Duderstadt maintained the file name for the record and added a sequence of numbers to the file name to indicate various versions. For example, the record 'Project Athena' progresses from Project Athena .92, Project Athena 1.0, 1.01, 1.2, 2.1, to Project Athena 2.21.
    - Speeches, 1986-1996; 821 original digital files
      A main avenue President Duderstadt utilized as a means to communicate his ideas, objectives, and university strategic plan was to get out into the community and talk. During his presidency, Duderstadt frequently made several speeches a day to groups on campus and across the state, thus making the Speeches series (821 original files, 1986-1996) the largest subseries in the University of Michigan Presidency subgroup. The early speech files from the years 1986 to 1992 were predominately composed using the MORE 3.1 outline program. However, after 1992 he drafted his speeches using a combination of MORE 3.1 and Microsoft Word 6.0. Major Speeches contained in this series include: The Cranbrook Address, The Challenge of K-12 Education, February, 1990, American Nuclear Society Keynote Address, A Future of Change, April, 1992, State Equity in Education Conference, The Michigan Mandate: A Progress Report, March, 1993, Vision 2017: The Third Century, November, 1993.
      Researchers should note that a list of key speeches by title, year, and location can be found in the digital file titled 'Accomplishments' located in the Strategy series. Also, note that several iterations of particular speeches can be found in the University of Michigan Presidency series. Duderstadt's file naming scheme reflects the change in a file by a series of numbers located after the file name.
      - 1986-1987 Speeches, 37 files
        - Niara Party, 1/11/1987
        - Physics-87, 1/18/1987
        - Rotary, 1/4/1986
        - MITN, 1/8/1987
        - Senate Assembly, 10/18/1986
        - Educ-Change, 11/10/1986
        - Honor Society, 11/10/1986
        - Legislators-86, 12/10/1986
        - Leadership, 12/20/1986
        - Rose Bowl, 12/26/1986
        - SPRL, 2/13/1987
        - Caltech, 2/16/1987
        - High Tech-3/87, 3/1/1987
        - Ed for Change, 3/22/1987
        - Genetics, 3/5/1987
        - E&V Conf, 3/6/1987
        - Sen Assem - 5/87, 5/17/1987
        - StrFnd-5/19, 5/18/1986
        - ASB-5/21, 5/21/1986
        - Challenge, 5/31/1986
        - MedSch-4/6, 5/6/1986
        - Nursing, 6/11/1987
        - Pluralism, 6/16/1987
        - BPC Talk, 6/26/1986
        - Minority Ed, 6/3/1987
        - Devel-6/30, 6/30/1987
        - Reunion-6/87, 6/6/1987
        - Chinese, 7/17/1986
        - AAAC-Min-II, 7/21/1987
        - Physics-85, 8/25/1985
        - EXPRES, 9/10/1986
        - Engineering, 9/18/1986
        - CRLT, 9/6/1986
        - Academic Affairs Picnic, 9/6/1986
        - Alumni Talk, 9/7/1986
        - LSA, 9/7/1986
      - 1987-1988 Speeches, 54 files
        - MLK Intro, 1/12/1988
        - Physics-87, 1/18/1987
        - SBR-88 Narrative, 10/13/1987
        - Football, 10/17/1987
        - Alumni Scholars, 10/17/1987
        - NIH, 10/20/1987
        - NIH Luncheon, 10/21/1987
        - ITI, 10/22/1987
        - Legislators, 10/22/1987
        - GR Econ-10/26, 10/25/1987
        - Solid State Lab, 10/25/1987
        - Yale-10/30, 10/29/1986
        - Homecoming, 10/31/1987
        - Faculty Dinners, 10/4/1987
        - Deans-HTS, 11/10/1987
        - Resident Talk, 11/12/1987
        - ICPSR, 11/14/1987
        - Football Bust, 11/30/1987
        - Grad Ed, 11/6/1987
        - SSC Testimony, 2/16/1988
        - Computer-Medicine, 2/19/1988
        - State Appropriations Test, 2/24/1988
        - Student-Athletes, 2/4/1987
        - Athletes Reception, 2/7/1988
        - Minority Faculty Recruiting, 2/9/1988
        - PIF-2/9/88, 2/9/1988
        - Sen Ass, 2016
        - Senate Assembly-9_87, 2016
        - U Seminar, 2016
        - 1987-1988 Speeches-Miscellaneous, 2016
        - UM-AAPS, 2016
        - Campus Trash, 2016
        - Chihiro Kikuchi Memorial, 2016
        - Traxler/Bloch, 3/14/1988
        - NASA ERCs, 3/23/1988
        - Scripps-Howard, 3/23/1988
        - US-Japan Conference, 4/14/1987
        - Yale-S&E-88, 4/18/1988
        - Deans TermEnd Dinner, 4/23/1988
        - Eng Comm-88, 4/30/1988
        - Radiogenic Dedication, 4/4/1988
        - Yale Talk, 4/7/1987
        - NSF/MSF Conference, 6/4/1988
        - Opening, 6/9/1988
        - New Faculty Welcome 2.0, 8/30/1987
        - Freshman Convocation 1.0, 9/6/1987
        - Grad Welcome 1.0, 9/6/1987
        - Deans/EO Kickoff, 9/7/1987
        - Minority Welcome 1.0, 9/7/1987
        - Parents Orientation 1.1, 9/7/1987
      - 1988-1989 Speeches, 124 files
        - MLK Opening, 1/14/1989
        - MLK-Business and Finance, 1/14/1989
        - MLK-Closing, 1/14/1989
        - MLK-Science Manpower Needs, 1/14/1989
        - MLK-Unity March, 1/15/1989
        - CBS Questions, 1/31/1989
        - Welcome Home, 1/4/1989
        - Rose Bowl Followup, 1/5/1989
        - Listen and Learn, 1/8/1989
        - EO/SACUA/Student Retreat, 1/9/1989
        - Faculty Awards, 10/1/1988
        - HBCU Remarks, 10/1/1988
        - Talks 10/17/88, 10/15/1988
        - Medical Center Reception, 10/16/1988
        - Lead Network 1.2, 10/16/1988
        - UMF Dedication, 10/16/1988
        - Alumni-Short, 10/16/1988
        - Canhan Dedication, 10/16/1988
        - Inauguration Remarks List, 10/2/1988
        - Legislative Luncheon, 10/2/1988
        - Student Inaug Address 1.5, 10/2/1988
        - Volunteer Leadership, 10/2/1988
        - Speech Topics, 10/28/1988
        - Booth Newspapers, 10/28/1988
        - Talk List, 10/31/1988
        - Inaug Intro, 10/4/1988
        - Inaug Breakfast, 10/5/1988
        - Inauguration 1.9S, 10/5/1988
        - Inaug Stu Picnic, 10/5/1988
        - Inaug Luncheon, 10/5/1988
        - New Detroit, 11/1/1988
        - Medical Education, 11/20/1988
        - Football Bust-88, 11/27/1988
        - Costs of Education, 11/27/1988
        - Lead Network Talk 1.3, 11/27/1988
        - Lead Network 1.3, 11/27/1988
        - New Detroit Presentation, 11/4/1988